Guide to the André Kertész photographs, 1919-1984 RL.11566
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
André Kertész photographs
1919-1984
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Archive of Documentary Arts (Duke University)
Kertész, André
RL.11566
1.0 Linear Feet 2 boxes 31 photographic prints 8x10 and 11x14 inches
Collection of 31 black-and-white photographs by André Kertész provides a sampling of his compositional styles and topical interests. Taken from 1919 through 1984, the images chiefly feature street scenes from Paris (1920-1984), and several each from Budapest and New York City. There are also two female nude studies from his 1930s series "Distortions," two still lifes, and several landscapes. The majority of the gelatin silver prints are sized 8x10 inches, with four measuring 11x14 inches. On the backs are various markings, including dates and identifying marks by Kertész and others, with many bearing a Kertész estate stamp. Acquired as part of the Archive of Documentary Arts at Duke University.
Content Description
Collection of 31 black-and-white prints by noted photographer André Kertész provides a portfolio representing the full range of his compositional styles and topical interests. Taken from 1919 through the 1980s, the end years of his career, the images chiefly feature street scenes from Paris in the 1920s and 1930s and 1980s, with a few street scenes from Budapest (1919 and 1920), and a handful from New York City from his later years in that city, with one from 1939. There are two photographs from the 1930s series "Distortions," featuring female nudes with distortion effects. Several images include cats and dogs. There are a handful of landscapes with no known location, and two still lifes.
The majority of the prints are sized 8x10 inches, with four measuring 11x14 inches. They bear various markings on the backs, including crop marks, dates, and identifying marks by Kertész and others. All but five are marked with the Kertész estate stamp; several bear the photographer's stamp.
Acquired as part of the Archive of Documentary Arts at Duke University.
Arrangement
Prints are arranged chronologically by year.
Biographical Note
Born in Hungary, André Kertész (1894-1985) was known for his mastery of composition with light, his experimental photography, and for his street photography and portraiture. After living in Paris for a decade and developing his style as a photographer and photojournalist, he immigrated to the U.S. in 1936, where he continued his work. After World War II, Kertész became a naturalized U.S. citizen, returning in subsequent years to France and other places around the world to take photographs.
After practicing as a photojournalist in Europe and in the United States for a good part of his career, in the early 1960s he pulled away from this type of work for good, and enjoyed a period of growing and widespread acknowledgment of the quality of his work. He died in 1985 in New York City.
Conditions Governing Access
Collection is open for research. Images may only be used for educational, non-commercial purposes; any other use requires the photographer's permission.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The André Kertész photographs were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 2017.
Related Materials
Related collection: William Gedney photographs and papers, 1887, circa 1920, 1940-1998 and undated, bulk 1955-1989, David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University.
This related collection contains extensive street photographs taken in Paris France, as well as an interview with André Kertész speaking about photography, recorded on audiocassette from a WNET station radio program, January 9, 1979; comes with transcription.
Documentary photographers -- United States; Documentary photography -- France; Nudes (representations); Photographers -- Europe; Photojournalists -- Europe; Street photography -- France -- Paris; Street photography -- New York (State) -- New York; Budapest (Hungary) -- Photographs; New York (N.Y.) -- Photographs; Paris (France) -- Photographs; Paris (France) -- Social life and customs; Black-and-white photographs; Gelatin silver prints; Portrait photography; Still lifes; Archive of Documentary Arts (Duke University); Kertész, André
- Buildings on hillside, Budafolk, 1919 (Box 1, Image RL.11566-P-001)
  Scope and Contents
  Budafolk is a neighborhood in Budapest, Hungary.
  Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
  8x10 inches. Printed later.
- Hazy day, Budapest, 1920 (Box 2, Image RL.11566-P-028)
  11x14 inches. Printed later.
- Place de la Concorde fountain, Paris, 1925 (Box 1, Image RL.11566-P-002)
  10x8 inches. Printed later.
- Mimi Pinson's house, Montmartre, 1926 (Box 1, Image RL.11566-P-003)
- Black cat with sculpture and newspaper, Paris, 1926 (Box 1, Image RL.11566-P-004)
- Marche aux Puces, Paris, 1926 (Box 1, Image RL.11566-P-005)
- Near the Porte De Vanves, Paris (horses), 1926 (Box 1, Image RL.11566-P-006)
- On the quai near Saint Michel, Paris, 1926 (Box 1, Image RL.11566-P-007)
- Near Pont de Grenelle, Paris (boat launch), 1927 (Box 1, Image RL.11566-P-008)
- Four men gathered at wood stove in Paris bistro, 1927 (Box 1, Image RL.11566-P-009)
- Artist painting near Pont St. Denis, Paris, 1927 (Box 1, Image RL.11566-P-010)
- Canal Saint Martin, Paris (bridge over river, tugboats), 1927 (Box 1, Image RL.11566-P-011)
- Children playing, Tuileries Garden, Paris, 1928 (Box 1, Image RL.11566-P-012)
- Canal Saint Martin, Paris (opening locks), 1929 (Box 1, Image RL.11566-P-013)
- Rue du Chateau, Paris (Eiffel tower in distance), 1929 (Box 1, Image RL.11566-P-014)
- Man in window, Savoy, France, 1929 (Box 1, Image RL.11566-P-015)
- St. Jean de Luze, France (market still life with dog), 1931 (Box 1, Image RL.11566-P-016)
- Alone, Paris, 1931 (Box 1, Image RL.11566-P-017)
- Rue Bourgeois, Paris (woman and 7 cats), 1931 (Box 1, Image RL.11566-P-018)
- Distortion #156, Paris, 1933 (Box 2, Image RL.11566-P-029)
  14x11 inches. Printed later.
- Distortion #172, 1933 (Box 2, Image RL.11566-P-030)
- Rockefeller Center (parade of elephants and plane), 1939 (Box 2, Image RL.11566-P-031)
- Tudor City, New York (pigeon, 08-25-62 #32), 1962 (Box 1, Image RL.11566-P-019)
- Outdoor statuary (08-22-72, #5), 1972 (Box 1, Image RL.11566-P-020)
- Trees on hill with clouds (05-04-78, #10A), 1978 (Box 1, Image RL.11566-P-021)
  8x10 inches. Printed circa 1978.
- Still life (ceramic church, snail and figure on windowsill, 11-05-78, #5), 1978 (Box 1, Image RL.11566-P-022)
- Still life (winged sculpture on papers, reflection, 10-25-78, #14A), 1978 (Box 1, Image RL.11566-P-023)
- Paris (cat on car hood, near Notre Dame Hotel), circa 1970s (Box 1, Image RL.11566-P-024)
  8x10 inches, unknown print date.
- Île Saint-Louis, Paris (poultry display with art poster, 12-29-82, #19), 1982 (Box 1, Image RL.11566-P-025)
  10x8 inches. Printed circa 1982.
- Trees and streetlamp at dusk (12-17-82, #35A), 1982 (Box 1, Image RL.11566-P-026)
  8x10 inches. Printed circa 1982.
- People sitting along Seine, view of Notre Dame from rear, circa 1984 (Box 1, Image RL.11566-P-027)